Guide to the Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo papers
1963-1983
SC0772
Rosaldo, Michelle Zimbalist
12.5 Linear feet (9 boxes)
The papers include class files from the course The Female Experience: Victorian Heritage, Part II, containing the syllabus, lecture notes, exam questions, minutes of the teaching collective (1978-79), and the course reader; one file of Rosaldo's lectures on women's position in "simpler" societies, which includes one letter from Rosaldo to Jane Collier, Oct. 31, 1975; and typescript papers with some published versions of Rosaldo's book reviews and articles, 1972-1983. An addition to the collection in 2006 (largely unprocessed) includes course files, 1973-1981; research notes, including field notes from 1963 and 1966; correspondence; reprints of her articles; her undergraduate papers; and condolence letters to Renato Rosaldo after her death, 1981.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was given to the Stanford University Archives by Jane F. Collier in 2005 and by Renato Rosaldo in 2006.
Information about Access
Letters of recommendation in Accession ARCH-2006-166, Box 8 are restricted. This collection is otherwise open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo earned her doctorate in social anthropology at Harvard in 1972. She joined Stanford's faculty in the Department of Anthropology in the same year and quickly rose to national prominence as an anthropologist, sociolinguist, and feminist scholar. She was co-chair of Stanford's first Committee on Feminist Studies (1980-1981) and helped develop the curriculum for the Program in Feminist Studies. In 1979 she was awarded the Dinkelspiel Award for outstanding service to undergraduate education. She died from an accidental fall while conducting research in the Philippines in 1981.
Description of the Collection
The papers include class files from the course The Female Experience: Victorian Heritage, Part II, containing the syllabus, lecture notes, exam questions, minutes of the teaching collective (1978-79), and the course reader; one file of Rosaldo's lectures on women's position in "simpler" societies, which includes one letter from Rosaldo to Jane Collier, Oct. 31, 1975; and typescript papers with some published versions of Rosaldo's book reviews and articles, 1972-1983. An addition to the collection in 2006 (largely unprocessed) includes course files, 1973-81; research notes, including field notes from 1963 and 1966; correspondence; reprints of her articles; her undergraduate papers; and condolence letters to Renato Rosaldo after her death, 1981.
Access Terms
Collier, Jane Fishburne.; Rosaldo, Michelle Zimbalist; Anthropology--Study and teaching.; Women--History--Study and teaching (higher)
Collection Contents
- Papers, Series 1
  - Female Experience: Victorian Heritage, Part II – class file, 1979 spring (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Female Experience: Victorian Heritage, Part II – course reader (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lectures on women's position in "simpler" societies, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book reviews, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles on Ilongot speech (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Magic and Medicine: a Problem in Cultural Analysis, conference paper, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Metaphors and Folk Classification, Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, Vol. 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Moral/Analytic Dilemmas Posed by the Intersection of Feminism and Social Science, conference paper, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Shame of Headhunters and the Autonomy of Self, published and unpublished versions, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Towards an Anthropology of Self and Feeling, published and unpublished versions, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Use and Abuse of Anthropology: Reflections on Feminism and Cross-cultural Understanding, Signs, 1980 spring (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2006-166
  - Mostly unsorted class materials with some correspondence and 1 bound notebook, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Ling 50/Anth 180, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anth 142, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anthro 252 hostage parade article (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Symbolic, 1981 winter (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Anth 152, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Anth 252, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Victorian Heritage II, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Anth 244, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Royalty statements, letters of reference (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - MZR tenure (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Faculty records, course evaluations (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Official correspondence and recommendations (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Women's bibliography (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rosaldo/Collier work – correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rosaldo/Collier work – text (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rosaldo/Collier work – outlines, lectures, notes (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rosaldo/Collier work – research (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Anth 230, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Anth 163, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Ilongot research (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Soil test forms, Kasibu, Nueva Viscaya, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Notes on Ilongot songs (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Notes on Ilongot spells (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Notes on Ilongot spells (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Notes on Ilongot magic (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Metaphors and Hypotheses (re Ilongot genres) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ilongot myth (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Phonology: Kakidugon Bugkalut," typescript paper (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ilongot phonology (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous notes on Ilongot (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Topo maps of Luzon (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence (3 folders), 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Envelope of correspondence (Box 3)
  - "Shelly's current correspondence" (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Women's Book [Women, Culture and Society] correspondence (2 envelopes, 2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (2 envelopes) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, unorganized and not in folders (Box 4)
  - Field notes, 1963, and photographs and postcards that accompanied them (Box 5)
  - Z notes field notes and interviews?), 1966 (Box 5)
  - Other notebooks and loose notes (many not written in English) (Box 5)
  - Typescript papers (her own undergraduate), 1960s (Box 5)
  - 2 Notebooks (Spanish class?) (Box 6)
  - Class evaluations from her anthropology class, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Box of condolence letters to Renato Rosaldo after her death, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Other materials relating to her death and memorial fund, including audiocassette of memorial service (Box 6)
  - Her reprints, typescript papers, book reviews, panel commentary, and correspondence, 1965-1981 (Box 7)
  - Class materials – syllabi, lecture outlines, bibliographies, exam questions, 1970s (Box 7)
  - Letters of recommendation [restricted] (Box 8)